<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title>Conjurer</title>
  <link href="http://nunb.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://nunb.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2011-12-01T23:35:51+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://nunb.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Nandan Bagchee</name>
    
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title>Migrating Content</title>
    <link href="http://nunb.github.com/blog/2011/12/01/migrating-content/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-01T18:44:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://nunb.github.com/blog/2011/12/01/migrating-content</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am in the process of migrating my various writings from around the web here, and re-tagging all content.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Clojure Conj the Second</title>
    <link href="http://nunb.github.com/blog/2011/11/16/clojure-conj-the-second/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-16T13:03:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://nunb.github.com/blog/2011/11/16/clojure-conj-the-second</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am still trying to distill some thoughts from the 2nd Clojure Conj in Raleigh (Nov 9th-12th).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile my &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/nandanbagchee/&quot;&gt;twitter page&lt;/a&gt; has some impressions from that period, and some might be visible in the sidebar on this page.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Communication &amp; Collaboration</title>
    <link href="http://nunb.github.com/blog/2011/10/01/communication-and-collaboration/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-01T18:25:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://nunb.github.com/blog/2011/10/01/communication-and-collaboration</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been reading a book on the history of Bayesian statistics. Separately I&amp;#8217;ve
also been a fan of Neal Stephenson&amp;#8217;s Baroque cycle, which I read a few years ago,
and sections of the book on Bayes&amp;#8217; Theorem cover the same time period the Baroque Cycle
is set in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things that really stood out for me while reading these book was the
sense of time dilation that people then accepted as a matter of course. Or, in
reverse terms, the incredible instant-gratification culture we live with today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, then, huge, world changing discoveries in the sciences might have made barely a
ripple due to the inefficiencies of dissemination. This was not only due to
limited venues for such dispersal, but even where such venues existed, the
topic of the discovery had no sympathetic ear  to fall upon, for example, a
Royal Society meeting where the one like-minded collaborator was unable to
attend due to, say, the difficulties of travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few months ago, a friend of mine showed me a mathematical paper he had
written that had been accepted on Arxiv (an online journal that is not
mendaciously profit oriented, unlike the zillions of other journals out there).
In contrast, Ramanujan went for years without recognition in Western mathematical circles, writing his work
down in notebooks, which he then sent en-masse to a mentor in England. What if
they&amp;#8217;d been lost on the sea-voyage? The possibility of shipwreck certainly
existed in 1912. The transmission of information was an exercise fraught with hazard, and the useful end-points
for such delivery limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or for another example, the other day I was doing some research into skip-list
data-structures and was able to easily access the original papers involved,
using tools such as Google Scholar and just plain searching. Even a few years ago, this kind of
information was hard to come by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some ways though, even today, I feel the value of collaboration is under-appreciated. Partly we have
conquered the problem of not having a medium by going over to the other extreme &amp;#8211; that of
having lots of channels, but they are all now incredibly noisy. The value of collaboration is under-appreciated
because of the pain one has to go through to find the &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; collaborator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a book by Gary Taubes, a science writer, he refers to the fact that those on
the practising side of medicine are far removed from the latest discoveries on
the research side. If a discovery does not have a corporation disseminating
that information, it is unlikely to get through to the practitioners, most of
whom are working off knowledge gleaned from textbooks read during their college
years, decades in the past. (In medical specialities, this is less of a problem.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bazaar model has been conspicuously successful in software. In fact,
companies have been spun out of various facets of the bazaar model, for
example, github. But it has not been applied, afaik, to its full potential
in research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even as a novice researcher, I find it difficult to keep track of all the
information I have gathered, and finding collaborators for my multifarious
interests is so difficult, that I barely even try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine how much the world would benefit if it were easy to organize knowledge
and gain collaborators from a personal perspective? Unlike say, google or
google scholar, this kind of network would spread outwards, from me as an
individual to others in the same field, decentralized instead of centralized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why should matching algorithms exist (and by hyped by) dating websites, when they
are so much more applicable to researchers with similar interests? An academic who&amp;#8217;s
listed their research interests is much more likely to be honest and comprehensive
than a teenager on a dating website like okcupid &amp;#8211; which means the conclusions drawn
by the matching algorithm are much more likely to be robust.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
